Walter F. McCaleb Papers
Walter F. McCaleb Papers
1892-1968
McCaleb, Walter Flavius, 1873-1967.
22.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American author. Correspondence, family and business; manuscript essays, plays, poems, short stories, and novels; notebooks; and clippings.
149769
Biographical History
Walter Flavius McCaleb (1873-1967) was an American author of novels, plays, poetry, essays and non-fiction works regarding U.S. history.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Walter F. McCaleb Papers consists of material relating to his activities as an author of novels, plays, poetry, essays and non-fiction, with special emphasis on the Southwest, banking and finance in the U.S. and Mexico, and correspondence as an officer in the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers. The collection contains autobiographical material, correspondence, writings (both published material and manuscripts), and memorabilia.
Autobiographical material contains autobiographical and genealogical material, student papers, family correspondence. Also included here are photographs, notes, and printed material relating to McCaleb's bicycle trip to Mexico in 1898.
Correspondence contains incoming and outgoing correspondence of a non-family nature; some deals with McCaleb's political and business concerns. Correspondence relating to Franklin D. Roosevelt is foldered separately, as is McCaleb's correspondence with his publishers.
Writings consists of manuscripts, typescripts, and typescript copies for books (both fiction and non-fiction), essays, plays, poetry, and short stories.
Memorabilia includes lists of McCaleb's library holdings, newsletters from the Aaron Burr Association, tax receipts, printed material, clippings, notebooks, and other assorted items.
Published material contains books by McCaleb.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has received only minimal processing. Items are listed in the inventory below in alphabetical order, but within the boxes material remains in the order it was received.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; McCaleb, Walter Flavius, 1873-1967.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Authors, American.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Essays.; Manuscripts for publication.; Notebooks.; Poems.; Authors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Autobiographical material
  - Miscellaneous, 1892-1968; autobiographical and genealogical material, student papers, correspondence with family members (Box 1-2)
  - Bicycle trip to Mexico, 1898; printed material, photographs, typescripts, handwritten material (Box 3)
  - Portrait of McCaleb, 1898; small black-and-white photograph (Box 3)
- Correspondence
  - Business, professional and political; incoming and outgoing, 1901-1967 (Box 4-12)
  - Mayfield, John S., 1959-1968; includes print item related to dedication of Mayfield Library and comments on Swinburne solicited by JM (Box 13)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1936; undated; correspondence, manuscripts, typescripts, relating to requests made to FDR, FDR's 1936 campaign, Harper and Bros., S. E. Burr Jr., S. H. Wandell (Box 14)
  - Naylor Co. (publishers), 1950-1968 (Box 15)
- Memorabilia
  - WFM's library listing (Box 40)
  - List of books owned by WFM (Box 40)
  - Newsletters of the Aaron Burr Association (Box 40)
  - Typescript copies and plans for McCaleb Adding Machine Co., 1910s (Box 40)
  - Tax receipts (Box 40)
  - Graphics (Box 40)
  - Print items (Box 40-41)
  - Manuscript notebooks, agendas (Box 42)
  - Print clippings (Box 43)
- Writings
  - Books (fiction)
    - Bill and Emmie, manuscripts, typescripts (Box 38)
    - Columbine, manuscripts, typescripts (Box 38)
    - Pedro, Pat and Me, manuscripts, typescripts (Box 37)
    - Peter Wembleton, manuscripts, typescripts (Box 38)
  - Books (nonfiction)
    - A Child's History of Texas, manuscripts, typescripts (Box 39)
    - The Mier Expedition, manuscripts, typescripts (Box 39)
    - New Light on Aaron Burr, manuscripts, typescripts (Box 16-17)
    - The Santa Fe Expedition, manuscripts, typescripts (Box 39)
    - The Spanish Missions of Texas, manuscripts, typescripts (Box 39)
    - Texas and the Mexican War, manuscripts, typescripts (Box 39)
  - Essays
    - Miscellaneous, on national and international themes, circa 1930-1960 (Box 18-20)
  - Poetry
    - Miscellaneous, manuscripts and typescripts (Box 21-24)
  - Plays
    - A-C, manuscripts and typescripts (Box 25)
    - C-F, manuscripts and typescripts (Box 26)
    - H-J, manuscripts and typescripts (Box 27)
    - O-U, manuscripts and typescripts (Box 28)
  - Short stories
    - A-H, manuscripts and typescripts (Box 29)
    - H-P, manuscripts and typescripts (Box 30)
    - R-W, manuscripts and typescripts (Box 31)
    - "Don Pedro", manuscripts and typescripts (Box 32)
    - "The Gold Finder", manuscripts and typescripts (Box 33)
    - "Helmet's Tale", manuscripts and typescripts (Box 34)
    - Margarita, manuscripts and typescripts (Box 35-36)
  - Published material
    - Books by WFM (Box 44-45)